<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<a name="bnc"></a>
<h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
    <h3>Motivations for a clinical profile registry</h3>
    <p>Data science succeeds when broad domains of data can be explored to advance discovery, validation, or
    knowledge application.  The NCATS Translator program seeks to demonstrate translational queries across linkable
    databases spanning basic science repositories (e.g. gene, protein, pathway) to clinical manifestations
    (e.g. phenotype, symptoms, drug response).  The nature of running translational queries requires overcoming
    barriers to the use and access to such databases. Access to clinical information in particular is invariably a
    challenge.  To address this problem in part, we posited creating a clinical profile registry as a surrogate data
    resource to enable executing translational queries.</p>
    <p>The vision for a clinical profile registry is to include clinical profiles that are machine readable and
    consisting of aggregated statistics and facts about disease behavior derived from patient records. Profiles would
    reduce patient-level, specific elements into statistical characterizations about a group of patients sharing
    phenotype, disease, or other cohort defining properties.  For example, a fanconi anemia profile would include
    summary information about serum hemoglobin levels  (e.g., mean, standard deviation, median value, and decile
    cut-points of the distribution) across a group of patients with this condition.  It is also attractive to
    consider demographic subsets of a clinical profile e.g., summary information about clinical profile measures by
        race, sex, and age groups.</p>
    <p>The Clinicalprofile resource represents the statistical features of a defined population. Predetermined subgroup 
        settings are going to outline the contents of a clinical profile. The resource is going to cover different dimensions
        of the clinical settings, including:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>Lab result statistics and inferences</li>
        <li>Medication statistics and inferences</li>
        <li>Procedure statistics and inferences</li>
        <li>Cross tabulations for patient informaiton</li>
        <li>Correlation analysis</li>
    </ul>
    

</div>

<!-- (recommended): 
<div>
<h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
<p>
Explains how this resource relates to others. Particularly important is to differentiate between appropriate usages for related resources when an implementer might be confused about what to reference when.
</p>
</div>
-->

<div>
<h2>Background and Context</h2>
<h3>Clinical profile data model requirements</h3>
<p>As an initial step to defining the model requirements for a clinical profile, we identify core data
    (demographics, medications, common lab values, and coded information such as co-morbidities and procedures),
    some condition-specific measures (e.g pulmonary function tests for patients for asthma) that are readily available
    in electronic health records (EHR).  The transition from patient-level data into a clinical profile would require
    reducing those data into to appropriate summary measures. For example, a comorbidity may be rendered in a
    clinical profile as the fraction of persons in a population expressing that comorbidity.
    Additionally, clinical profiles might express a degree of correlation between variables when they are significant,
    such as hemoglobin and hematocrit.</p>
<p>Temporal considerations have potential to greatly complicate requirements for clinical profiles.  As an achievable
    goal, we can enable subsetting profiles into pre- and post- event (e.g., treatment, diagnosis) subsets.  Also
    important for many conditions, is an ability to  define a clinical profile of persons suffering from acute
    exacerbations vs relatively stable periods.</p>
<p>Different research teams have been trying hard to generate shareable patient data in all health-related contexts,
    like nursing, medical imaging and genomic fields these years(1).</p>
</div>


</div>
